A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Dwellings-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - "L" General 1980-1995 (Box 12)
    Lafayette's Camp, Keswick Hunt; Lamb House (Virginia Lamb), Yancey Mills, 1900; Lamm House, (Catholic Diocese of Richmond, owner), Earlysville, mid 19th century, ca. 1900; Landrum- Irving House, Charlottesville, 1908; Larmour House, Albemarle, ca. 1900; Leake-Farish House, Charlottesville, 1850s, 1920; Leitch House, (James A. Leitch House), Charlottesville, 1910; Leitch-Munday House, Charlottesville, 1828; Lewis-Lammey House, Charlottesville, 1897; Liberty Hall, Farmington Hunt; Limestone Spring Farm, Shadwell area, ca. 1820; Linden Lane Farm, Keswick, 1930s; Lindsay House, (Daniel House), Scottsville, mid 19th century; Little Black Mountain, Albemarle, 1971; Little Raynham, Albemarle, 20th century; Little Virginia, (School/Office relocated from The Meadows), Lindsay, late 19th century, ca. 1900; Lochlyn, Albemarle, 1950s, 1985; Lochlyn Cottage, Albemarle, 1980; Locust Avenue House, early 20th century; Locust Grove House, Locust Grove Improvement Company House #1, Charlottesville, ca. 1894-1895; Locust Grove Improvement Company House #2, Charlottesville, ca. 1894-1895, 1908; Locust Shade, (Windcrest), Albemarle, ca. 1850; Lofland Place, Albemarle, ca. 1860; Log Cabin, Carters Bridge; Log House, Camp Carter; Log House, Albemarle, razed; Log House Farm, Albemarle, 20th century; Lone Oak Farm, Albemarle, 20th century; Lonleat, (Kennett W. Hinks House), Turner Mountain, Ivy, ca. 1962; Long Ridge, Albemarle; Lost Valley Farm, Albemarle; Lotti House, Charlottesville, 1882-1889; Lower Sherwood, (Mt. Airy site), Albemalre, 1952; Lydea, Woodbridge, late 19th century; Lyndhall Apartments, University Way, 1915
  - Macon-Victorius House, (Paul Victorius Home; James Madison Curtis Home), Charlottesville, 1914, 1944 1995 (Box 12)
  - Madras Hill, near Greenwood, 1825, 1920s, 1930s, 1975 1987-1991 (Box 12)
  - Mallory-Spencer House, Charlottesville, 1891 n.d. (Box 12)
  - Malvern (Millhouse, Oakland, Mayor Benjamin Wheeler Home; Gerald Lindsay Home; S. O. White Home), Albemarle, ca. 1820, 1969-1970 1997-1998 (Box 12)
  - Manahan House, (Home of Anastasia, wife of John Manahan), Charlottesville, 1960 1991-1995 (Box 12)
  - Maple Hill, (old site of Maple Hill Cottage), Albemarle, 1914, 1976 1983 (Box 12)
  - Maple Hill Cottage, (Giles Home; Harrison Home; George T. Omohundro Home), Albemarle, ca. 1820, moved 1976 1990 (Box 12)
  - Marcha Hill, near Scottsville n.d. (Box 12)
  - Marshall-Rucker House, (William J. Rucker Home), Charlottesville, 1894, 1930 1975-1998 (Box 12)
  - Massie-Wills Townhouse, (Frederick Wills Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1830 1965-1993 (Box 12)
  - Matthews House, (site of Lewis Leschot Shop & Library), Charlottesville, ca. 1836 1995-1997 (Box 13)
  - Maupin-Bibb House, (Chapman W. Maupin Home; William A. Bibb Home), Charlottesville, early 19th century 1991-1996 (Box 13)
  - Maupin House, ("Creek Dave" Maupin House), Albemarle, mid 1830s 1976 (Box 13)
  - Maxfield, (Belvoir; Fairy Fort; The Creek Farm; Hommes or Money Boys School), Keswick, ca. 1764, burned 1835, moved to Milton then to Cismont 1978-1991 (Box 13)
  - McAllister-Andrews House, (J. B. Andrews Home), Charlottesville, 1875, 1896, 1985 1980-1994 (Box 13)
  - McCue House, (Afton Farm), Albemarle, ca. 1883 1991-1999 (Box 13)
  - Meadow Bluffs, (Southern Comfort; Harris Plantation; The Farm), Free Union, ca. 1790, 1891, 1967 1955-1976 (Box 13)
  - Meadow Creek, Albemarle, late 19th century 1994 (Box 13)
  - Meadowbrook, Greenwood, ca. 1800 1990-1992 (Box 13)
  - Meadows, The, (Little Virginia), Albemarle (main house over Louisa line), ca. 1810, late 19th century 1995 (Box 13)
  - Meadows, The, (James O. Carr House; House Tract of Meadow Creek Farm; Peyton House), Charlottesville, ca. 1872, razed 1992 1992-1996 (Box 13)
  - Mechum River Farm, Batesville, ca. 1810, 1840s 1989-1992 (Box 13)
  - Meridien, Free Union, ca. 1840 1989 (Box 13)
  - Meriwether, Farmington Hunt, 20th century n.d. (Box 13)
  - Merrie Mill Plantation, (Edgefield), Cobham, 1857, ca. 1900 1979-1999 (Box 13)
  - Merry Oaks, Burnley, ca. 1830, 1947, 1950 1990-1997 (Box 13)
  - Meyers House, Charlottesville, 1925 1994 (Box 13)
  - Michie House, Saint Margaret's, Cobham, ca. 1785 1992 (Box 13)
  - Midmont, (Bernard Chamberlain Home; William C. Chamberlain Home; Mary Lewis Clarkson Craven Home; Thomas Walker Maury Home; Jesse Pitman Lewis owner), Charlottesville, early 19th century, mid 19th century, ca. 1870 1989 (Box 13)
  - Midway, (Riverdale Farm; Huntsmoor), Farmington Hunt, 1765, 1807, 1820, ca. 1930 1977-1998 (Box 13)
  - Midway Farm, Crozet, ca. 1810, 1930s 1984-1995 (Box 13)
  - Millburne, Albemarle, Charlottesville, ca. 1800 1992 (Box 13)
  - Miller House, Charlottesville, 1902, 1987 1993 (Box 13)
  - Miller House, Earlysville, 1927 1993 (Box 13)
  - Millhaven, Advance Mills, ca. 1920 1982-1991 (Box 13)
  - Millstream Farm, Advance Mills, ca. 1866, 1965 n.d. (Box 13)
  - Milton Farm, Milton, early 19th century, ca. 1915 1982 (Box 13)
  - Mini-Acres, Keene, 1890 n.d. (Box 13)
  - Minor-Nelson House, (and Minor-Nelson Sanitarium), Charlottesville, ca. 1827-1840 1991-1999 (Box 13)
  - Mirador, (El Mirador; Millburne site), 1842, 1897, 1921, 1930, 1976 1974-1994 (Box 13)
  - Monroe Hill, (Lower Plantation; Major Edmund Broadus Home; Arthur P. Brockenbrough Home; Captain John M. Perry Home), University of Virginia, ca. 1789, 1817, 1848, 1929-1930 1990-1999 (Box 13)
  - Montalto, (Pattersons Mountain; Carters Mountain; Browns Mountain; Repose; Kinrose; Carter Ridge; Mountaintop Farm; Mount Alto), Albemarle, ca. 1900 1995 (Box 13)
  - Montebello, (George Wilson Spooner, Jr. Home; Charles Scott Venable Home; William Mynn Thorton Home; Bruns Home; Mrs. Eva Warren Home; John Zack Holladay, Sr. Home; Douglas Buffum Home; Gundy Home; Isaac Kimber Moran Home; Hardy Cross Dillard Home; Frank Kaulback, Jr. Home; Marion B. Peavy Home; Robert Sweeney Home), Stadium Road, Charlottesville, 1819-1820 1982-1994 (Box 13)
  - Montesano, Charlottesville, 1939-1940 1981 (Box 13)
  - Monticello 1, (A Jefferson Farm), Carters Mountain, 1768-1796 1981 (Box 13)
  - Monticello 2, (A Jefferson Farm), Carters Mountain, 1796-1809, 1935, 1953-1954 1973-1995 (Box 14)
  - Monticello, Inn at (see Inn at Monticello) 1995 (Box 14)
  - Monticola, (Fowles Tavern), Howardsville, early 1840s 1991-1995 (Box 14)
  - Mooreland, (Poplar Springs), Albemarle, 1854 1991 (Box 14)
  - Mooreland (Old), (Locust Grove (?); William Moore Home; Charles Wingfield Home; Marcus Durrett Home), Albemarle, 1750, 1930s 1987-1995 (Box 14)
  - Morea, (John M. Perry, landowner; Richard Thomas Walker Duke Home; Little Morea, attached; Boarding House), Spring Lane, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, ca. 1835, 1847, 1962 1976-1985 (Box 14)
  - Morrisena, Warren, early 19th century 1977-1992 (Box 14)
  - Morris House, (Anne C. Morris Home), Charlottesville, 1845 1991 (Box 14)
  - Morrowdale, Albemarle, near White Hall, 19th century n.d. (Box 14)
  - Morven 1, (Indian Camp Slave Quarters), Simeon, ca. 1796 1993 (Box 14)
  - Morven 2, (Whitney Stone Home; Margaret Patterson Home), Simeon, ca. 1820, 1926, 1928, 1936 1976-1997 (Box 14)
  - Morven, (Dr. Edward F. Birckhead Home; Dr. Edward H. Birckhead Home), Albemarle, 18th century 1994-2000 (Box 14)
  - Mount Air (Cole-Bishop House; Ferneyhough Home; McVey Home; Coles Home; Bishop Home), Proffit, 18th century, ca. 1865 1991-1997 (Box 14)
  - Mount Air (Christopher Hudson House; Mount Ayr; Judge John Schuyler Moon Winter Home), Carters Bridge, 18th century 1991 (Box 14)
  - Mount Air Farm, White Hall, 1914 1975 (Box 14)
  - Mount Amour, (Crystal Mountain Farm; Socrates Maupin Home), Greenwood, ca. 1790, ca. 1830 1981-1991 (Box 14)
  - Mount Comfort, (across from) Woodlands, Albemarle, ca. 1800 1979-1997 (Box 15)
  - Mount Eagle 1, (Charles Lilburn Lewis Home; Craven Peyton Home), Albemarle, 18th century 1991 (Box 15)
  - Mount Eagle 2, (Robert Gentry Home), Boyd Tavern, 1846 1976 (Box 15)
  - Mount Fair, (Captain Bazaleel Brown, Sr. Home; Dean Edmund S. Campbell Home), Browns Cove, 1845 1966-2000 (Box 15)
  - Mount Ida, (David Ross Home; William Leitch Home), Keene, 1790s, 1996 relocated 1997 (Box 15)
  - Mount Pleasant, ca. 1830, Scottsville, mid 19th century, early 20th century 1980-1998 (Box 15)
  - Mount Prospect, (Charles & Christopher Hudson Home; Charles Wingfield, Sr. Home), Biscuit Run Valley, ca. 1762 n.d. (Box 15)
  - Mount Walla, (Mount Wallow; Peter Field Jefferson, owner), Scottsville, ca. 1770 1993 (Box 15)
  - Mount Warren (Governor Wilson Cary Nicholas House; William Tapscott Home), Warren, ca. 1780, burned 1927 1973-1996 (Box 15)
  - Mount Warren Farm (Wilson Cary Nicholas, owner; Wolcott Rives, owner), Esmont, ca. 1900 1991-1996 (Box 15)
  - Mountain Grove, (Benjamin Harris, owner), Green Mountain, 1803-1804 1966-2000 (Box 15)
  - Mountain View, Albemarle, ca. 1810, ca. 1825 1976 (Box 15)
  - Mountain View Farm, Albemarle, early 19th century n.d. (Box 15)
  - Music Hall (Captain James H. Terrell Home), Cismont, late 18th century, razed, ca. 1910 n.d. (Box 15)
  - "M" General 1955-1996 (Box 15)
    Magruder House, Farmington, 1952; Lawton Mahan House, Farmington; Mahanes House, Charlottesville, William Mahone House, Keene, 1900; Maple Hill, Greenwood. ca. 1915; Mariah, Farmington Hunt, 20th century; Marlewood Hall, Greenwood, 20th century; Marshall-Dabney-Shackleford-Cubbage House, (George B. Marshall; Walter D. Dabney; Gertrude Shackleford; Ann H. Cubbage), Charlottesville, ca. 1892; Marshall-Edwards House, (George B. Marshall; Samuel W. Edwards), Charlottesville, ca. 1894; Marshall Farm, Earlysville, late 19th century; Martin House, Charlottesville; Mason Lane, Charlottesville, 1927; Massie House, Covesville, 1900; Massie-Dabney House, Charlottesville, 1895; Massie-Smith Townhouse, Charlottesville, ca. 1830; Massland Farm; Keswick Hunt;Maupin's Place, Albemarle, ca. 1810; Pleasent Maupin Homestead, Free Union, late 18th century; Benjamin Maupin House, Free Union, 1830s-1850s; Nathaniel Maupin House, (Guy Via House), Albemarle, ca. 1826; Maxwell Mountain House, (John Maxwell Home), Covesville, ca. 1751
    McAllister House, Batesville, late 19th century; Cecil McAllister Home, Sugar Hollow, mid 19th century, 1935; McCarthy House, Albemarle, 1830; McCrory House, Ednam Forest, 20th century; McCue-Sprouse House, Crozet, ca. 1880-1900; McGregor House, Howardsville, 1840, 1980s; McIntire House, (Paul McIntire Home), Charlottesville, razed; McKennie-Miller House, Charlottesville, ca. 1850; McMurdo-Michael House, (James Harry Michael, Jr. House), Charlottesville, 1899; Meadelands, (Richard K. Meade Home; Llewellyn), Charlottesville, 1854; Meadow View, Albemarle; Mechunk Creek Stables, Keswick Hunt, ca. 1910; Merifields, Cismont, late 19th century; Merlands, Albemarle, late 18th century
    Michie-Morris House, Charlottesville, 1898; Middle Mountain Farm, Sugar Hollow, 1934-1943; Midstream, Albemarle, 20th century; Miller School Road House, Albemarle, 1931; Millstone, Albemarle, 1920s; Millwood Manor, Albemarle; Minor Court Apartments, University Avenue, 1896, 1927; Minor-Gilmer House, Charlottesville, 1873; Miramont, University Circle, 1914
    Monticello Wine Company House, Charlottesville, ca. 1884; Moon House, (Brooks-Martin Log House; Layman House), Batesville, mid 19th century; Moon House, (Chancellor House), Scottsville, early 19th century; Moon-Henderson House, Charlottesville, late 19th century; Moore-Wingfield House, Charlottesville, 1885; Lanny P. Morris House, Albemarle, early 20th century; Morris Home, (Clark Sutherland Home), Albemarle, ca. 1824; Mt. Airy, Albemarle, early 1920s; Mount Merrie Farm, Albemarle; Mountain Hollow Farm, Greenwood, 19th century; Mountain Meadows, Greenwood; Mountain View, (Harkaway), Crozet, 1930; Myers House, Charlottesville, 1925
  - Neilson House, (John Neilson, owner; Captain Christopher L. Fowler Home), Charlottesville, 1862 1982-1991 (Box 15)
  - Nelson House, (R. B. Nelson, owner), Charlottesville, 1857-1862 1996-1998 (Box 15)
  - New Shadwell, (Colonel Frank G. Ruffin, owner; Punch Bowl Farm; Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Jr. Home), Albemarle, 18th century, 1841, 1923 interior burned, 1946 1975-1976 (Box 15)
  - New Woodville, (Elizabeth & Sally Coles Hotel; Jaquelin T. Robertson Home), Green Mountain, 1892, 1989 1980-1995 (Box 15)
  - Nimmo House, Albemarle, 1870-1873 1979 (Box 15)
  - Nockamellie, Albemarle, 20th century n.d. (Box 15)
  - Normandale, (Melrose; Carr House), Albemarle, 18th century, 1975-1976 n.d. (Box 15)
  - Norris House, (Joseph Norris, owner), Charlottesville, ca. 1850; 1953 razed for Monticello Hotel parking) 1990-1991 (Box 15)
  - Norris-McCue Townhouses, (Norris-McCue Building), Charlottesville, 1820s 1976 (Box 15)
  - Northwood, Charlottesville, 1843 n.d. (Box 15)
  - Northwoods, Ivy, ca. 1870, 1989 1982-1994 (Box 15)
  - Nutmeg, (Charles T. Taylor, owner; Charles Hudson, 1730 patent), Carters Bridge, ca. 1940, 1977 1986-1988 (Box 15)
  - Nydrie, (Harry Douglas Forsyth, owner; Ray Alan Van Clief Home), ca. 1898, 1932 1980 (Box 15)
  - Nydrie (Log Saddlebag House; converted into school), Green Mountain 1990 (Box 15)
  - "N" General n.d. (Box 15)
    Nalls House, Charlottesville. 1885; Narrow Lane Farm, Albemarle, mid 19th century; Nay House, Covesville, late 19th century; Nimmo-Sims House, Charlottesville, ca. 1875)
  - Oak Crest, (Gibson House; Benjamin Sowell House), Alberene, early 19th century 1977-1993 (Box 16)
  - Oak Forest, Farmington, ca. 1933 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Oak Grove, (Meadowbrook Farm; Hugh Rice Morris House), ca. 1790 1980 (Box 16)
  - Oak Hill, (Gambrel Place; November Hill; Francis W. Meriwether Home; Miss Selma Nelson Home), Stony Point, ca. 1820, burned 1953 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Oak Hill (Tommy Renwick, owner), Farmington Hunt, 1930s 1977 (Box 16)
  - Oak Hill, (Garrett House), Charlottesville, razed 1950s 1992-1993 (Box 16)
  - Oak Lawn, (Oaklawn), Earlysville, 18th century, 1965 1976-1983 (Box 16)
  - Oak Lawn (Oak Grove; Reverend James Fife Home), Charlottesville, 1822, ca. 1900 1979-1999 (Box 16)
  - Oaklands, (Benjamin Wood, owner; converted to bungalow), Woodville, Ivy, ca. 1845, ca. 1916 1976-1979 (Box 16)
  - Oakleigh, (Countess Judith Gyurky Home), Port-a-Ferry, ca. 1905, ca. 1939 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Oaks, The, (Judge Cornwell Franklin Home), Keswick, ca. 1834, ca. 1952, 1991 1979-1990 (Box 16)
  - Oakwood, (W. H. Harris), Fan Mountain, ca. 1795 1981-1993 (Box 16)
  - Old Hall, (James W. Mason House; used as hospital by Dr. Lottie Moon), 1830 1978-1997 (Box 16)
  - Old Longwood, (Michie House), Albemarle, ca. 1825, 1900 1976-1991 (Box 16)
  - Oldham, (James Oldham House), Mechums River, ca. 1830, 1920s 1976-1997 (Box 16)
  - Orangedale, (William Dinsmore Home; Joseph Watson Home), Charlottesville, 1820s, late 19th century n.d. (Box 16)
  - "O" General 1976-1984 (Box 16)
    Oak Hill, (A. M. Taylor House), Greenwood, 1916; Oak Hill, Howardsville, 1845; Oak Lane, Charlottesville, 1890-1898, ca. 1955; Oakdale, Keswick; Oakencroft, (Felicia Warburg Rogan, owner), Charlottesville; Oakhurst, Green Mountain, 20th century; Oakmont, (Isetta), Green Mountain, ca. 1912; Oakwold, Scottsville, ca. 1914, ca. 1961; Oakwood, Albemarle, 20th century; Octavo, Greenwood, ca. 1820s; October Light Horse Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1870; Old Edgewood, Albemarle, ca. 1850; Old Homestead, Albemarle, ca. 1825; Old Paradise, Greenwood, ca. 1850
  - Pandora Farm, Cobham, 1840 1977 (Box 16)
  - Pantops 2, (James Leitch House; Sampson Home; Pantops Academy; Paul G. McIntire, owner- University of Virginia), Albemarle, ca. 1797, 1877, 1884, 1938 1998 (Box 16)
  - Pantops 3, (James Creek House), Albemarle, 1937 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Patches, Farmington, 1933 1992 (Box 16)
  - Patton Mansion, (John Patton House; Judge J. C. Brooks Home; Mary Fitch Home), Charlottesville, 1820s, 1850s 1980 (Box 16)
  - Pen Park, (William Hotopp Home), Rivanna River, ante 1750, 1920s burned, ca. 1972 razed n.d. (Box 16)
  - Piedmont, (Reuben Maury House), University of Virginia, Charlottesville, ca. 1830, late 19th century 1986-1995 (Box 16)
  - Piedmont, (William Wallace House), Greenwood, ca. 1805-1809, 1816 1990-1998 (Box 16)
  - Piedmont, (J. J. Pace Home, T. Ed Powers Home; Harris Home; Civil War Hospital), White Hall, ca. 1850, ca. 1853, ca. 1972 1956-1987 (Box 16)
  - Piedmont Manor, (Girls School; movies Virginia and Giant filmed here), Stony Point, 1845, ca. 1939 1978 (Box 16)
  - Pigeon Top Farm, Millington, ante 1870 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Pine Knot, Keene, (Plain Dealing Cottage; President Theodore Roosevelt Hunting Lodge), 1903, ca. 1905 1978-1999 (Box 16)
  - Pines, (Terrell House; Tucks Home; Pettus Home; Bowlesville), Cismont, late 18th century, 1812 1992 (Box 16)
  - Pireus House, (William H. Meriwether House), Charlottesville, ca. 1835 1995 (Box 16)
  - Pitts-Inge House, (Inge Home & Store; George P. Inge, Sr. Home; converted into Bull Alley Restaurant); West Main Street, Charlottesville, 1820, 1890, 1980s, 1989 fire 1979-1990 (Box 16)
  - Plain Dealing, Keene, 1761, 1789, 1934, 1980s, 1994 (3 folders) 1977-1998 (Box 17)
  - Plainview Farm, (Ballard-Maupin House; Thomas Maupin House; Thomas Ballard House; Bradford Hall; George and Elizabeth Neff owners), Free Union area, Albemarle, ca. 1760, 1994 1994-1997 (Box 17)
  - Pleasant Hill, (Pleasant View; Childress-Turner House), Scottsville district, ca. 1801 1975-1991 (Box 17)
  - Pleasant Hill, (Samuel Barksdale; Rice Garland Barksdale; Senator Edward O. McCue Home), Albemarle, early 19th century, 1850s, 1942 1973-1992 (Box 17)
  - Pleasant Retreat, (Wiant Place; Benjamin Brown, Jr. Home; bricks used at Mirador), Browns Cove, ca. 1810, 1920s, razed 1930 1989-1996 (Box 17)
  - Plumb Pleasant, Crozet, early 19th century n.d. (Box 17)
  - Pomegranate, Crozet, ca. 1825, 1850s 1978-1996 (Box 17)
  - Port-A-Ferry, (Countess Judith Gyurky Home), Batesville, late 18th century, 1846 1997-1998 (Box 17)
  - Poorhouse 1, Garth Road, ca. 1806 1993 (Box 17)
  - Poorhouse 2, Keswick, ca. 1850, 1950s 1979-1994 (Box 17)
  - Poorhouse, (Old Poorhouse Log Saddlebag House), Keswick, ca. 1820 1979-1990 (Box 17)
  - Pounding Brook Farm, (Davis House), Albemarle, early 20th century 1978 (Box 17)
  - Powell-Ballard House, Albemarle, ca. 1900 n.d. (Box 17)
  - Price-Poore House, (Poore House), Charlottesville, ca. 1839 1993 (Box 17)
  - Prodigal, The, near Scottsville, mid 19th century 1975 (Box 17)
  - "P" General 1995-1998 (Box 17)
    Pace-Wranek House, Charlottesville, ca. 1884, 1955, 1957, 1958, razed 1997; Charles T. Page, Sr. House, Batesville, ca. 1905-1915; Page Brook, (Samuel Page Home), Red Hill, ca. 1883, early 20th century; Page-Burgess Home, Batesville, late 19th century; Pantops, Albemarle; Parr House, Charlottesville, ca. 1890; Parkview Farm, Crozet, 1979; Parrish Log House, Albemarle, 19th century; Parsons Green, Mechums River, 18th century; Patterson House, Crozet, 1900; Paxton Place, Charlottesville, ca. 1824
    Pendleton (Edmund C.) House, Charlottesville, 1920s; Perkins House, (Thomas Walker Gilmer), Charlottesville, ante 1863; Perley House, Charlottesville, 1889; Perley-Gleason House, Charlottesville, 1889; Petit House, Albemarle, ca. 1850; Peyton House, Ridge Street, Charlottesville, razed 1957 for fire station; Peyton House, (Hillcrest Apartments), 14th Street, Charlottesville, 1894, 1906, 1958, 1963, converted into apartments
    Piedmont Lodge, Cismont, ca. 1862; Phillips kitchen dependency (Thomas Rock Phillips, restoration), Scottsville, 1770-1790; Pierremont, Crozet, ca. 1900-1920; Pinchem-Slyly House, (Double C Farm), ca. 1792; 2011 Pinetop Road, Charlottesville; Piney Grove, near Brookhill, 1885; Pireus Row House, Woolen Mills, 1880s; Pleasants House, Charlottesville, 1936; Pocket Plantation; Present Value Farm, Free Union, ca. 1877; Preston Court Apartments, Charlottesville; Pugh-Mawyer House, Batesville, early 20th century; Purcell House, Charlottesville, 1880s; Purvis-Seay House, Charlottesville, 1896; Pytchley, Crozet
    1977-1995 Quiet Entry, (Virginia Hurt House), Green Mountain, ca. 1825, early 19th century, early 1940s
  - "Q" General 1974-1995 (Box 17)
    Quandry, Carters Bridge/Blenheim, 1860; The Quarters, (Quarter Plantation; Borodaile), Albemarle, ca. 1750, ca. 1950, 1910, 1988; Quick Cabin, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Quietude, Keswick Hunt, 1910; Quinta Sarita, Charlottesville
  - Ragged Mountain Farm, (Pace Place), Ragged Mountains, Ivy, ca. 1800, 1963 1978-1993 (Box 18)
  - Ramsay, (William H. Langhorne House), Albemarle, ca. 1900, 1930s n.d. (Box 18)
  - Randolph House, (Dale House), Charlottesville, 1910 1994-1995 (Box 18)
  - Recoleta, (Harry Rogers Pratt House), Charlottesville, 1939-1940 1944 (Box 18)
  - Red Acres, (Lorelei; Maple Hill), Farmington Hunt, 1868, 1930s 1980 (Box 18)
  - Red Clay Hill, Bellair, Charlottesville, 20th century 1991 (Box 18)
  - Red Hills, (Thomas Carr Home; Dr. Francis Carr Home), Albemarle, 1797, ca. 1805, ca. 1950 1957-1996 (Box 18)
  - Redbrook, (built on foundation of original Keeloma; Isaac White Home; George W. Stark Home), Albemarle, 1846 1991 (Box 18)
  - Redcliffe, (McMurdo House; John G. Yancey Home), Albemarle, ca. 1901 1979-1991 (Box 18)
  - Redlands, (Edward Carter Home; Robert Carter Home; West Oak; Forest Hill; Civil War hospital), Carters Bridge, 1789, 1798, 1808, 1952 1977-1999 (Box 18)
  - Redlands Club, (Edward Valentine Home; Swan Tavern site; Samuel Leitch, Jr. Home), Charlottesville, 1832, 1920 1978-1995 (Box 18)
  - Refuge, (Mount Gallant; Jones Plantation; John Neilson Home), Keene, 18th century, late 19th century 1991 (Box 18)
  - Richlands, (Edward Coles Home), ca. 1853, ca. 1890 1995 (Box 18)
  - Ricochet, Albemarle, 19th century 1993-1995 (Box 18)
  - Ridge Street Historic District Survey (various houses) 1994 (Box 18)
  - Ridgely, (William E. Boeing House), Greenwood, ca. 1910 1991-1995 (Box 18)
  - Ridgeway, (Classical School; James Dinsmore Home; Hugh Minor Home; Franklin Minor Home), Albemarle, ca. 1809, ca. 1850, 1870s, ca. 1989 1978-1996 (Box 18)
  - Riggory, The, (John Carr Home; Franklin Minor Home; Hugh Minor Home; Classical School for Boys), Eastham, 1796, 1849, 1950s 1978-1999 (Box 18)
  - Rivanna Farm, (Mrs. Audrey Emery Home; Gale Hill ruins), Albemarle, 1957-1958 1983-1984 (Box 18)
  - River Lawn, (Colonel Joseph Joplin Home; Argyle), Esmont, ca. 1765, ca. 1800 1991 (Box 18)
  - Riverdale, Charlottesville, mid 19th century, 1912 1996 (Box 18)
  - Riverdell, (Yancey Millhouse), Yancey Mills, ca. 1820 1991-1992 (Box 18)
  - Riverside, (James McCullock House; Millington House; Millington Post Office), Albemarle, ca. 1800 1976 (Box 18)
  - Riverview, (John Snead Home; Littleberry Moon Home; Riverside), Scottsville, 1817, 1825, ca. 1865 1975-1993 (Box 18)
  - Robertson House, (Judge William J. Robertson Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1850 1993-1999 (Box 18)
  - Robin Hill, Farmington, ca. 1790, ca. 1810 1977-1995 (Box 18)
  - Rock Hill, (William Dinsmore Home; James Leitch owner; S. P. Hargrove Home; Eugene Bradbury Home), Charlottesville, 1820s 1963-1995 (Box 19)
  - Rocks, The, (Abbell Home), Ivy, ca. 1830, ca. 1850, 1930s 1978-1985 (Box 19)
  - Rolling Acres, (Dunkum House; Norrilen Place; Helen L. Hammond Home), Albemarle, 1820s 1978-1999 (Box 19)
  - Rose Hill, (William Wirt Home; Craven Home; Sandidge Home), Charlottesville, late 18th century, razed 1933 n.d. (Box 19)
  - Rose Hill, (Mrs. William R. Massie Home; John D. Craven Home; Rose Cottage; based on Mt. Airy), Greenwood, 1930-1931 1991-1995 (Box 19)
  - Rose Valley, (John Jones Home), Crozet, 1820, 1854 1976-1990 (Box 19)
  - Rosemont, (B. Charles Baker Home), Ivy, Albemarle, ca. 1900, 1920s 1978-1995 (Box 19)